Preliminary Inventory to the Tadeusz Romer Papers, 1913-1975
Hoover Institution Archives
Tadeusz Romer Papers,
1913-1975
77004
Romer, Tadeusz
9 microfilm reels (3.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, speeches and writings, reports, telegrams, minutes of meetings, clippings, and printed matter, relating to political events in Poland, Polish foreign relations, and Polish emigré politics
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Public Archives of Canada.
Access Points
Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych; Katyn Forest Massacre, 1940; Poles in foreign countries; Refugees; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history; World War, 1939-1945--Governments in exile; World War, 1939-1945--Poland; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees; Germany; Germany--Foreign relations--Poland; Poland; Poland--Foreign relations; Poland--Foreign relations--Germany; Poland--Foreign relations--Soviet Union; Poland--History--1918-1945; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945; Soviet Union; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Poland; Warsaw (Poland)--History--Uprising of 1944; Diplomats--Poland; Statesmen--Poland
Preliminary Inventory Microfilms
- African colonies - manuscript copies of treaties, notes, 1913-14 (Reel 1 - 2, Volume Volume 1)
- Paris Peace Conference - memoranda, correspondence, 1918-19
- Polish-French Alliance (1921) - memoranda, notes, treaty draft, 1918-1966
- Polish treaties and agreements - memoranda, drafts, correspondence, 1925-1931
- Warsaw - memoranda, correspondence, 1922-1935
- Rome - memoranda, official correspondence, printed matter, 1929-1935
- Japan - memoranda, correspondence, newsclippings, etc., dealing with Japanese Far Eastern activities, 1937-1940
- Japan - SUPRA, 1940-41 (Reel 3 - 4, Volume Volume 2)
- Shanghai Consulate-General - correspondence, telegrams, 1941-42
- Lorenco Marques, 1942
- Events leading to war in Europe - memoranda, n.d., 1947
- U.S.S.R. - General - minutes of meetings with senior Soviet political figures, messages between Ambassador Romer and the Polish Government-in-Exile (London), 1939-1952
- Polish Deportees in the U.S.S.R. - primarily correspondence from Romer to London on the condition of deportees in 1943, 1941-43
- High Commissioner in Cairo, 1943-44 (Reel 5, Volume Volume 3)
- Katyn - these papers include correspondence related to the U.S. Congressional investigation into the Katyn massacre (1952), 1943-1952, 1970
- General Wladyslaw Sikorski - primarily dealing with Sikorski's Middle East tour during which he was killed, 1943-47
- Newsclippings: Sikorski and Romer - primarily from 1943 and dealing with the events surrounding Sikorski's death, 1942-47, 1970, 1974
- London - General - reports, correspondence, minutes, 1942-43
- U.S.A. - primarily correspondence and reports from Ambassador Jan Ciechanowski on the American political scene, 1943-44
- Polish-Soviet border dispute - primarily papers dealing with the boundary dispute dated between the Teheran Conference (December 1943) and the Yalta Conference (February 1945), consisting of reports, memoranda, correspondence, and printed matter, 1942-1952
- Talks with Victor Lebedev (Soviet Ambassador to the Allied Governments in London), 1944
- The Warsaw Uprising (1 August - 2 October, 1944) - correspondence, memoranda, minutes, 1943-44, 1950, 1954
- Negotiations with Stalin and other Soviet leaders, minutes of meetings before and during the Warsaw Uprising, 1944
- Polish Armed Forces Abroad, 1941-44
- London - General - memoranda, minutes, correspondence, including material related to the Moscow Conference during the Warsaw Uprising, invitations to diplomatic functions, replies to invitations, calling cards, etc., 1943-44 (Reel 6, Volume Volume 4)
- Speeches by T. Romer, primarily from the war period, 1943-1975
- Organization and personnel of the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1943-44
- Germany - Polish-German relations before World War II, Polish interest in Germany during and after the war, 1940-1954
- Bulletin of the Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1943-45
- SAME AS REEL #6 (Reel 7)
- Assistance to refugees - memoranda, letters, booklets, 1941-1952 (Volume Volume 5)
- Romer's resignation as Minister of Foreign Affairs (22 November 1944), letters from London's diplomatic corps, 1944
- London - General - correspondence, newsclippings, memoranda, maps of Poland, 1944-48
- Peace Conferences: Yalta, Potsdam, Paris - newsclippings, 1945-1974
- Elections in Poland - memoranda, newsclippings, 1946
- Poland after the war - correspondence, 1946-1954
- The Hague European Congress - Agenda, correspondence, Romer's speech, reports, resolutions, notes, 1948
- U.S. Ambassador Joseph C. Grew - correspondence, booklets, 1940, 1948-1950
- Articles on the Polish Question by T. Romer, 1936-1966
- Miscellaneous memoranda by T. Romer, 1946-1965
- SAME AS REEL #7 (only Volume 5) (Reel 8 - 9)